Hamilton Cochran Papers
Hamilton Cochran Papers
1932-1960
Cochran, Hamilton, 1898-1977
5.0 linear ft.
Papers of the American author, novelist. Correspondence (1938-1965), mainly with publishers; manuscript articles, plays, poems, radio scripts, and stories; clippings by and about; photographs and scrapbooks.
149714
Biographical History
Hamilton Cochran (1898-1977) was an American writer of historical novels with a nautical background.
Born in West Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, Cochran attended Swarthmore Preparatory School but when World War I broke out in his senior year he left school and enlisted in the Coast Guard Academy in New London, Connecticut. He served 18 months on the USCGC Algonquin and then for a brief time in the Merchant Marine. Returning to school he majored in journalism at the University of Michigan and after graduation did advertising work in New York City. From 1931-1932 he served as Commissioner of Public Welfare for the island of St. Thomas in the Virgin Islands, where his interest in the history of the area, particularly the dramatic tales of pirates, resulted in his first book, These are the Virgin Islands (1937).
Cochran then joined the advertising department of the Saturday Evening Post and a year later was named manager of the automotive division. He worked for Standard Oil for several years and served in the Coast Guard again during World War II, but his main interest was sea travel, of which he logged more than 100,000 hours. Over his career he wrote thirteen books -- both fiction and non-fiction -- as well as numerous poems and articles. His best known title was Blockade Runners of the Confederacy. He and his wife, Enid Slee, had three daughters.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Hamilton Cochran Papers contains biographical material, book illustrations, correspondence, manuscripts, memorabilia, and printed material.
Biographical material contains a few assorted items related to Cochran's life and work.
Book illustrations contains original artwork (paintings, cover art, sketches, etc.) for five of Cochran's books.
Correspondence is both incoming and outgoing, mostly between Cochran and his publishers.
Manuscripts includes articles, books, plays, poems, radio talks, and speeches.
Memorabilia consists mostly of scrapbooks of clippings and other material about five of Cochran's books. There are also a few photographs.
A small amount of Printed material completes the collection, including clippings and published translations of two of Cochran's books in Swedish.
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence is arranged by name of correspondent. All other series are arranged alphabetically by title, topic, or type.
Subject and Genre Headings
Literature -- American Fiction; Cochran, Hamilton, 1898-1977.; Confederate States of America. -- Navy.; Authors, American.; Dueling -- History.; Novelists, American.; Historical fiction.; Pirates in literature.; Sea fiction.; Virgin Islands -- History.; United States -- History.; Confederate States of America -- History.; Articles.; Book illustrations.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Manuscripts for publication.; Photographs.; Poems.; Scrapbooks.; Authors.; Novelists.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Biographical material
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
- Book illustrations
  - Captain Ebony, original painting for book jacket, unknown artist (Oversize 1)
  - Noted American Duels and Hostile Encounters (Box 2)
  - Noted American Duels and Hostile Encounters (Oversize 1)
  - Rogue's Holiday, original painting for book jacket, by Paul Laune (Oversize 1)
  - These are the Virgin Islands, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - These are the Virgin Islands (Oversize 1)
  - Windward Passage, original painting for book jacket, unknown artist (Oversize 1)
- Correspondence
  - A-B (Box 1)
  - Bobbs-Merrill Company, Inc., 2 folders (Box 1)
  - C (Box 1)
  - Cochran, Joseph Wilson (father) (Box 1)
  - Curtis Publishing Company (Box 1)
  - D-G (Box 1)
  - Luther Hartwell Hodges (governor of North Carolina) (Box 1)
  - H-P, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Paul R. Reynolds and Son (Box 1)
  - Pearson, Drew (Box 1)
  - R-W and unknown, 2 folders (Box 1)
- Manuscripts
  - Articles and short stories
    - The Belfry (Box 1)
    - Blackbeard the Pirate (Box 1)
    - Brass Cannon (Box 1)
    - Cruising Among the Virgin Islands (Box 1)
    - Danger Patrol (Box 1)
    - Dark Fury, noted as "A sequel to Silver Shoals"; 2 copies (Box 1)
    - Dark Terror (Box 1)
    - Ever Ride an Auto-bug or a Poppy Car? (Box 1)
    - Fool's Folly (Box 1)
    - Heavy Honey (Box 1)
    - The "J. Wilkes Booth" Pistol, 3 versions, includes illustrations used and publisher letter (Box 1)
    - The Lost Treasure of Silver Shoals (Box 1)
    - Navy Frogmen Salvage Weapons from Sunken Blockade Runner (Box 1)
    - North Carolina's Arch-Pirate: Bloodthirsty Blackbeard Became Famous in Fact and Fiction (Box 1)
    - The Package (Box 1)
    - Roolye - Boolye (Box 1)
    - Rum Making Still Flourishes in the Virgin Islands! - but it's Bay Rum…World Famous Product of these West Indian Isles (Box 1)
    - Treasure Hunting (Box 3)
    - The Union Navy's "Atomic Bomb" (Box 3)
    - The Virgin Islands - Haunt of Bucaneers [sic] (Box 3)
    - Were-wolf (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous untitled (Box 3)
  - Books
    - A Cochran Chronicle, appears to be an unpublished semi-autobiographical account of Hamilton's family and life; 2 folders (Box 3)
    - The Dram Tree, ch. 1-21, "original long draft"; 7 folders (Box 3)
    - The Dram Tree, ch. 22-25, "original long draft" (Box 4)
    - Eruption of Mt. Pelé, "Ideas for a novel", includes handwritten pages, research notes, and letter to his publisher over new book ideas; never published (Box 2)
    - Our Naval War with the Caribbean Pirates 1800-1836, drafts A-C; appears to be unpublished; 6 folders (Box 4)
    - Pirate Wench, dDraft A, includes minor corrections and edits; 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Pirate Wench, draft B; 2 folders (Box 5)
    - These Are the Virgin Islands (Box 5)
    - Miscelllaneous, incomplete chapters, outline, pages. etc. (Box 5)
  - Plays
    - The Moon and Henry Morgan, under pen name of Otis Cochran (Box 5)
  - Poems
    - Miscellaneous, includes a couple of handwritten poems; one set of poems includes photos; 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Radio scripts
    - Buried Treasure, a series of 15 minute radio dramas; note on folder says these were produced in 1934 (Box 6)
    - Famous Pirates of the Southern Seas, different from "Buried Treasure" above; note says these were produced by radio station WHAM in Rochester, NY in 1934 (Box 6)
    - Gibraltar...Mighty Fortress Commanding Two Continents, according to note, "radio talk broadcast over station WHEC, Rochester, NY, February 16, 1932" (Box 6)
  - Speeches
    - Miscellaneous (Box 6)
- Memorabilia
  - Application for membership to the Society of Authors, Playwrights, and Composers (Box 6)
  - Photographs, includes Cochran, window display of books (Box 6)
  - Scrapbooks
    - Blockade Runners of the Confederacy (Oversize 2)
    - Captain Ebony (Oversize 2)
    - The Dram Tree (Box 6)
    - Silver Shoals (Oversize 3)
    - These are the Virgin Islands (Oversize 3)
- Printed material
  - Articles by, Sep 1953 (Box 6)
  - Book list, "New Books for Apr 1947 of the Athenaeum of Philadelphia" (Box 6)
  - Books by Cochran, Swedish editions
    - Kapten Morgan, translated by Sven Rydström; Stockholm: Forum, 1960; Swedish translation of Windward Passage (Box 2)
    - Silverbankarna, translated by Lisbeth Och Louis Renner; Stockholm: Forum, 1949; Swedish translation of Silver Shoals (Box 2)
  - Clipping (Box 6)